JAMES MAYOL

Cumberland, Rhode Island 401.659.4060 jamesmayol@yahoo.com

Summary Of Qualifications

A software engineer with more than 10 years of technical expertise including:

- Design, development and deployment of object oriented software applications
- Proficiency of various relational database systems
- Knowledge of software design patterns and best practices
- Design and development of web applications, and websites
- Ability to work in fast-paced environments following Agile methodologies
- Quick learner of concepts and technologies

Technical Expertise

C#, VB.NET, C/C++, Visual Basic, HTML, CSS, JavaScript, ASP.NET, XML, JSON MSSQL, MySQL, Entity Framework, LINQ, ODBC Windows Forms, Windows Services, MFC, WSA, Win32 API, WCF, SOAP, REST, DevExpress Microsoft Visual Studio, SQL Server Management Studio, Jira, Crucible, SmartCVS, TortoiseSVN, Wireshark, SoapUI

Professional Experience

Software Engineer 2012 to Present

Amazing Charts - West Warwick, RI

Designed, and developed an Electronic Health Record software solution in a multilayer architectural model. Integrated software to MSSQL, and third-party services. Performed high level and detailed designs to satisfy complex business requirements. Participated in all phases of development life-cycle using Agile methodologies.

- Developed, and maintained C#, and VB.NET applications using Visual Studio
- Used Entity Framework to perform database integration
- Created and updated stored procedures, views, and functions using T-SQL
- Used WCF technology to integrate to third-party vendors using SOAP and REST
- Converted legacy VB6 modules to .NET Framework
- Designed, and developed an ASP.NET MVC intranet web application to assist customer support during installation, and help desk calls
- Developed a service to allow doctors to distribute coupons for prescription drugs, which served as an extra revenue source for the company
- Interpreted requirements from government specifications for implementation, and product certification

Software Engineer 2005 to 2012

PURVIS Systems - Middletown, RI

Designed, developed, and implemented multithreaded software applications for various VoIP solutions in a service-oriented architectural model. Integrated software to various database engines. Participated

in the entire application development life-cycle, which included design, on-site deployment, and 24/7 support of escalated issues.

- Developed C++/MFC, and C# applications using Visual Studio
- Used ODBC and SQL database connector to perform database integration
- Designed, deployed, and administered MSSQL and MySQL databases
- Developed windows services to monitor network, and to manage software applications
- Used Wireshark network analyzer to track TCP/IP, and SIP network issues
- Implemented API calls to integrate to windows components, and third-party applications
- Modernized and normalized a database system used during the reconstructions of NAVY exercises
- Designed, and developed software for a fire station alerting system used for sending firemen critical and non-critical alarms via third-party visual and audible devices
- Designed and developed a scheduling and monitoring application that initiates, and manages critical notifications for rapidly contacting a large number of people over various types of communication protocols and technologies
- Designed and developed a text-to-speech and speech recognition application used by FDNY to perform voice quality tests and ensure clear audio communications between the central dispatching offices and over 235 firehouses throughout the city
- Developed and implemented a customized, highly-available VoIP communications solution for the modernization of FDNY's voice alarm system

Part-Time Computer Engineer

2004 to 2005

University of Massachusetts – Lowell, MA

Provided software, and hardware technical support for the University's library computer systems by installing hardware, and network software packages.

- Performed software testing, and debugged issues
- Developed, and deployed C++ windows services to monitor run-time status of various software applications

Part-Time HUB Supervisor

2003 to 2005

United Parcel Service - Chelmsford, MA

Managed a package sorting operation in a fast paced, and constantly changing environment while ensuring that strict safety and productivity goals were met. Actively communicated with other operations within the facility in order to achieve higher service standards.

- Developed a successful training program to assist in the certification of new sorters, which
 resulted in a more knowledgeable workforce, and a higher overall productivity of the facility
- Managed ten workers by improving their skill set, and maintaining their certification
- Provided constructive feedback, and performed demonstrations to improve safety and efficiency

Education

B.S.E.E., Merrimack College, 1998